Finding aid to the J. Kenneth Loughry records Archives.Loughry.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
J. Kenneth Loughry records, 1929, 1943-1971 (bulk 1945-1969)
Archives.Loughry.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
2.3 Linear feet (5 full-size document cases, 1 half-size document case)
Loughry, J. Kenneth, d. 1976
Trescher, George
Scope and Contents note
The J. Kenneth Loughry records contain documents from the Treasurer's office, including financial and investment-related reports, and correspondence related to the Metropolitan Museum’s Finance Committee from 1949 to 1962. They also include Loughry’s correspondence with Museum trustees and staff members and materials pertaining to the activities of the Cultural Institutions Group, of which the Metropolitan was a member organization, especially related to employee pension and insurance issues. The records include one folder each of budgetary analyses of the proposed merger of The Metropolitan Museum of Art with The Whitney Museum of American Art in 1944 and the Metropolitan’s centennial celebrations in 1970.
Records pertaining to The Metropolitan Museum of Art’s Board of Trustees, Finance Committee, legal proceedings, investments, and specific employee compensation information are restricted according to Museum policy.
Biographical note
J. Kenneth Loughry (1905-1976) served as Assistant Treasurer (1944-1947), Secretary of the Finance Committee (1947-1968), and Treasurer (1947-1968) of The Metropolitan Museum of Art. He retired prematurely in the autumn of 1968, citing reasons of health and other personal considerations. He lived in Fort Collins, Colorado, and was killed in an automobile accident in in Idaho Springs, Colorado, in April 1976. After graduating from Wesleyan University, Loughry had served as a certified public accountant with the firm of Lybrand, Ross Brothers & Montgomery (later Coopers & Lybrand) before joining the Metropolitan Museum’s staff.
Arrangement note
The J. Kenneth Loughry records are arranged in three series: I. Board of Trustees, II. Finance Committee Meetings, III. General Files.
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open for research.
Records pertaining to The Metropolitan Museum of Art’s Board of Trustees, Finance Committee, legal proceedings, investments, and specific employee compensation information are restricted according to Museum policy.
Related Archival Materials note
Loughry, Mr. and Mrs. J. Kenneth, 1944-, Office of the Secretary Records, Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). Board of Trustees.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). -- History; Administrative records; Correspondence; Reports
- Series I. Board of Trustees, Bulk, 1960-1969; 1950, 1960-1969
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Files in this series containing sensitive financial, personnel, and Board-related information are restricted, according to Museum policy.
  - Correspondence with members. Centennial Anniversary Committee., January 1966-March 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    General note
    Access note: Redacted copies of documents with salary information replace originals in this folder. Restricted documents may be accessed on or after September 6, 2051 at the discretion of Archives staff.
  - Correspondence with members. Centennial Anniversary Committee., April-October 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Access note: Redacted copies of documents with salary information replace originals in this folder. Restricted documents may be accessed on or after April 1, 2053 at the discretion of Archives staff.
  - Correspondence with members. Gifford, Walter S., April-October 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II. Finance Committee Meetings, 1943-1969
  This series contains privileged financial information and is restricted, according to Museum policy.
- Series III. General Files, 1929, 1943-1971
  Related Archival Materials note
  Museum Estates files, Office of the Secretary Records, Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes files related to the Metropolitan Museum's participation in the Cultural Institutions Group. Formed in 1869, the Cultural Institutions Group consists of representatives from privately endowed New York City cultural institutions that receive public funding, termed quasi-public institutions. The organization shares information on and lobbies for continued funding and benefits coverage from the City, including participation in city-operated pension plans for their employees. At this time, the Group consisted of representatives from the American Museum of Natural History, Brooklyn Academy of Music, Brooklyn Botanic Garden, The Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences, the Brooklyn Museum, Children’s Museum Brooklyn, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, The Museum of the City of New York, New York Aquarium, the New York Botanical Garden, the New York Public Library, New York Zoological Society, Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, the Staten Island Museum, and the Staten Island Zoological Society.
  Also included are files documenting the Munsey Park residential real estate development. When millionaire investor, real estate speculator, and newspaper owner Frank A. Munsey died in 1925, the greater part of his estate, with a final value of close to ten million dollars, was left to The Metropolitan Museum of Art. It was the largest monetary gift to date that the Museum had received. The estate included ownership of the Sun-Herald newspaper, The Mohican Stores grocery chain, and real estate holdings in Manhasset, NY, on the north shore of Long Island. Under the leadership of Museum President Robert DeForest, the Metropolitan Museum developed part of the land into a planned residential community called Munsey Park. It featured Colonial-style houses and streets named after American artists. The community’s first model home opened in 1928. By 1950 the Museum had sold the Munsey real estate interests to other developers, realizing an estimated four million dollars from these transactions.
  Works Consulted
  “Art museum sold Sun and Telegram.”New York Times, January 5, 1950.
  - Banking. Chase Bank (Manhattan, Paris)., 1947, 1950, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Access note: Redacted copies of documents with salary information replace originals in this folder. Restricted documents may be accessed on or after March 17, 2032, at the discretion of Archives staff.
  - Banking. Chemical Bank., 1959, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Banking. Fifth Avenue Bank, Bank of New York., 1943-1959, 1966, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Banking. Morgan Guaranty Trust., 1945, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Access note: Folder contains privileged financial information and is permanently restricted, according to Museum policy.
  - Banking. U.S. Trust Co., 1952-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Benefits. Fringe benefit survey., 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Access note: Documents with privileged financial information have been removed from this folder.
    See also: See also: III. General Files/ f. Cultural Institutions Group, 1964-1968 (5 folders).
  - Benefits. Fringe benefit survey. Report to Board of Trustees., 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Benefits. Retirement of women age 60 vs. 65., 1948-1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Benefits. Retirement plan, Aetna., July 1, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Benefits. Wage continuation plan., 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Casts and reproduction. Alva Studios., 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cloisters. Planting plan, from Olmstead Brothers., April-May 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Note: Oversized plan has been removed to flat file 18, drawer 1, folder 13.
  - Cloisters. Planting plan, from Olmstead Brothers. Oversized annotated planting map. (Flat-file 18/drawer 1, Folder 13)
    Note: Oversized material removed from box 2, folder 11.
  - Cultural Institutions Group., May 1960-November 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Note: Oversized materials have been removed to flat-file 18, drawer 1, folder 13.
  - Cultural Institutions Group. Oversized spreadsheets., September 15, 1960 (Flat-file 18/drawer 1, Folder 13)
    Note: Oversized materials removed from box 2, folder 12.
  - Cultural Institutions Group., 1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Note: Oversized material has been removed to flat-file 18, drawer 1, folder 13.
  - Cultural Institutions Group. Oversized spreadsheet., [1962] (Flat-file 18/drawer 1, Folder 13)
    Note: Oversized material removed from box 2, folder 13.
  - Cultural Institutions Group., 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Cultural Institutions Group., 1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Cultural Institutions Group. Oversized spreadsheets., [1964] (Flat-file 18/drawer 1, Folder 13)
    Note: Oversized materials removed from box 2, folder 15.
  - Cultural Institutions Group., 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Cultural Institutions Group., 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Cultural Institutions Group. New York City Cultural Council. Correspondence and memos., March-April 1968 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Grace Rainey Rogers Auditorium. Plans by Voorhees Walker Foley & Smith, architects and engineers., June 11, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Insurance. Aetna Life Insurance., 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Munsey bequest. Sun Herald Corporation., November 1960-October 1961 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Munsey Park. Correspondence to DeForest and Elder., 1938-1945 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Munsey Park. Limidend Housing Corporation, agent., 1928-1929 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Personnel. Human Rights Commission. Ethnic employment survey., 1963 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Personnel. Priest, Alan., 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Access note: Folder contains confidential personnel information and is restricted permanently, according to Museum policy.
  - Personnel. Priest, Alan. Litigation., 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Publications. Report on picture books by Sterling A. Callisen., May 3, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Publications. Report on policy by Marshall Davidson., September 1948 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Rewald, John, transactions including 1946 purchase from Mrs. Lucien Pissaro., October 1946-July 1947 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Treasurer's office. Resolution and governance., May 1929 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Note: From the files of H.W. Kent who served as The Metropolitan Museum of Art's Secretary from 1913 to 1940.
  - War protection. Offsite storage Colorado Springs, West Point., 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - War protection. Offsite storage Colorado Springs, West Point., 1955-1958, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Whitney Museum of Art. Merger., 1944-1948 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Whitney Museum of Art. Merger. Oversized spreadsheets., 1940-1944 (Flat-file 18/drawer 1, Folder 13)
    Note: Oversized materials removed from box 6, folder 16.
  - Whitney Museum of Art. Suspense account., 1943-1948 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Access note: Redacted copies of documents with salary information replace originals in this folder. Restricted documents may be accessed on or after January 1, 2033 at the discretion of Archives staff.